Guide to the Margaret Callaghan Papers AIA.059
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Margaret Callaghan Papers
1925-2010
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Callaghan, Margaret
AIA.059
10.59 Linear Feet in 5 record cartons, 1 half manuscript box, 7 flat file folders, 4 oversize boxes, 2 card boxes, and 1 folder in shared housing
Margaret Callaghan is an active member of the New York City Armagh community, having served as the chairperson for Armagh's Welfare Committee, the Past President of the Lt. Patrick J. Walsh Division 29 of the Ladies Ancient Order of Hibernians (AOH), and the Past County President of the New York State Ladies AOH. This collection contains photographs, memoranda, correspondence, event programs, newspaper clippings, and financial records documenting Callaghan's involvement with the County Armagh Men's P&B (Patriotic and Benevolent) Association and subject files related to the New York Irish American community and political events in Northern Ireland. The collection illustrates how social organizations created and maintained cultural communities in the United States while retaining a connection to an ancestral homeland.
Arrangement
This collection is divided into three series:
Series I: County Armagh Men's P&B Association Files
Series II: Subject Files
Series III: Ancient Order of Hibernians, Ladies Auxiliary.
Series are arranged alphabetically, with further chronological arrangement for extended runs of similar materials as appropriate.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Related Archival Materials
Archives of Irish America County Societies Collection (AIA 003)
Archives of Irish America Collection on the Ancient Order of Hibernians (AIA 046)
United Irish Counties Association Records (AIA 056)
Scope and Content Note
This collection contains photographs, memoranda, correspondence, event programs, newspaper clippings, and financial records documenting Margaret Callaghan's involvement with the County Armagh Men's P&B (Patriotic and Benevolent) Association and the Ladies Auxiliary of the Ancient Order of Hibernians, as well as the associations' history more broadly. The majority of materials include programs and souvenir journals from the society's annual ball and dinner dances ranging from the late 1920s to the early 2000s. Other materials document the associations' cultural, social, and political activities, including bus outings and sporting clubs. The collection also contains a series of subject files with content related to the New York Irish American community and political events in Northern Ireland (especially Armagh), including folders on Cardinal Tomás Ó Fiaich. The collection illustrates how social organizations, such as the Armagh Men's P&B Association and the Ladies Ancient Order of Hibernians, created and maintained cultural communities in the United States while also retaining a connection to an ancestral homeland.
Biographical Note
Margaret Callaghan was born in New York City to Peter (originally from Cornahove, County Armagh) and Catherine "Kitty" Callaghan. Since childhood, Callaghan has been an active member of the New York Armagh community, marching in the St. Patrick's Day Parade for the county at age three. Her father, Peter Callaghan, was the President of the Armagh Men's P&B (Patriotic and Benevolent) Association from 1937-1939. The family remained involved in the city's Irish American community for decades with Margaret serving as the chairperson for Armagh's Welfare Committee, the Past President of the Lt. Patrick J. Walsh Division 29 of the Ladies Ancient Order of Hibernians (AOH), and the Past County President of the New York State Ladies AOH. Since 1971 she has marched in the city's St. Patrick's Day Parade for the Ladies AOH and for County Armagh.
Source:
Irish Echo, 19 April 1986.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Margaret Callaghan in 2010. The accession number associated with this gift is 2010.071. An addition to the collection, comprising Series III., was donated in February of 2014.
Irish Americans -- Societies, etc.; Irish Americans -- Ethnic identity.; Irish Americans -- New York (N.Y.) -- Social life and customs.; Irish Americans -- Social life and customs.; Armagh (Northern Ireland); Ancient Order of Hibernians
- Series I: County Armagh Men's P&B Association Files, 1925-2010; 5.67 Linear Feet in 3 record cartons, 2 oversize flat boxes, 7 flat file folders, 1 half manuscript box, and 1 folder in shared housing
  - 9th Annual Communion Breakfast, 1949 (Flat-file-folder 8, Tray 2)
  - 22nd Annual Bus Ride, 1954 (Flat-file-folder 5, Tray 2)
  - 26th Annual Outing (Kruckers), 1953 (Flat-file-folder 6, Tray 2)
  - Address Lists, 1950-1958, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Annual Ball Photographs, circa 1925-2009 (Box 1, Folder 2, Box 11, Folder 1-6)
  - Annual Ball Souvenir Journal, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Annual Ball Souvenir Journal, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Annual Ball Souvenir Journal, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Annual Ball Souvenir Journal, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Annual Ball Souvenir Journal, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Annual Ball Souvenir Journal, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Annual Ball Souvenir Journal, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Annual Ball Souvenir Journal, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Annual Ball Souvenir Journal, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Annual Ball Souvenir Journal, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Annual Ball Souvenir Journal, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Annual Ball Souvenir Journal, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Annual Ball Souvenir Journal, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Annual Ball Souvenir Journal, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Annual Ball Souvenir Journal, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Annual Ball Souvenir Journal, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Annual Ball Souvenir Journal, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Annual Ball Souvenir Journal, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Annual Ball Souvenir Journal, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Annual Ball Souvenir Journal, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Annual Ball Souvenir Journal, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Annual Ball Souvenir Journal, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Annual Ball Souvenir Journal, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Annual Ball Souvenir Journal, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Annual Ball Souvenir Journal, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Annual Ball Souvenir Journal, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Annual Ball Souvenir Journal, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Annual Ball Souvenir Journal, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Annual Ball Souvenir Journal, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Annual Ball Souvenir Journal, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Annual Ball Souvenir Journal, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Annual Ball Souvenir Journal, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Annual Ball Souvenir Journal, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Annual Ball Souvenir Journal, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Annual Ball Souvenir Journal, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Annual Ball Souvenir Journal, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Annual Ball Souvenir Journal, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Annual Bus Ride and Outing, 1956 (Flat-file-folder 7, Tray 2)
  - Annual Ball Souvenir Journal, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Annual Outing, 1950 (Flat-file-folder 4, Tray 2)
  - Armagh 100th Anniversary Marina Del Ray Photographs, 1994 (Box Shared Tamiment 157, Folder 17)
  - Armagh Ladies Auxiliary Ball Photographs, 1932-1935 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - The Bard, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Benefits, circa 1990 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - British Overseas Airways Corporation (BOAC), 1964 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Bus Rides, undated (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - By-laws, 1986-2006 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Centennial Celebration, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 1, Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Charter, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Chartered Flights, 1961-1968 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Constitution, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Dinner Dance, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Dinner Dance, 1971-1973 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Dinner Dance, 1974-1976 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Dinner Dance, 1977-1979 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Dinner Dance, 1980-1982 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Dinner Dance, 1983, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Dinner Dance, 1986-1987 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Dinner Dance, 1988-1989 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Dinner Dance, 1990-1991 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Dinner Dance, 1992-1993 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Dinner Dance, 1995-1996 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Dinner Dance, 1998-1999 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Dinner Dance, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Dinner Dance and Party Photographs, 1946-1963 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Event Notices, 1961-1999 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Financial Reports, 1951-1975 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Financial Reports, 1979-1980 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Financial Reports, 1986-1989 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Financial Reports, 1990-1991 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Financial Reports, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Financial Reports, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Financial Reports, 1995-1997 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Football Club of New York: Dinner Dance, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Football Club of New York: Dinner Dance, 1990, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Football Club of New York: Victory Celebration Dance, 1994, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - History and Directory, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Gaelic Football: General, 1953, 2003 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Gaelic Football Club of New York: Anniversary Dinner Dance, 2004-2005 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Gaelic Football Club of New York: Anniversary Dinner Dance, 2006, 2008 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Gaelic Football Club of New York: Anniversary Dinner Dance, 2009-2010 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Glenwood Landing, 1933 (Flat-file-folder 3, Tray 2)
  - Gramercy Commercial Photo, undated (Flat-file-folder 9, Tray 3)
  - "In Celebration of the Lives of Peter, Catherine (Kitty), Francis, and Margaret Callaghan and Their Armagh Attachment", 1994 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Invitations, 1939, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Ladies Auxiliary: Emigrant Industrial Savings Bank passbook, 1935-1938 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Ladies Auxiliary: Cinderella Dance ticket, 1932 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Ladies Auxiliary: General, 1924-1935 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Ladies Auxiliary: Treasurer's Book, 1931-1935 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Moll; The Year of the Hiker, 1992, undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - "My Armagh Memories", 1994 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1945-1986 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Officers, 1931-1987 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - O'Dwyer, William, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - O'Hanlon, James, undated (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Photographs: General, 1938-1949 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Photographs: General, 1956-1993 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Piper's Band Newspaper Clipping, 1932 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Plaque, undated (Box 10)
  - Slieve Guilion View, Nov 1986 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Table Layouts, 1977-1983 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Table Listings, 1974-1990 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Wallet, 1946 (Box 3, Folder 21)
- Series II: Subject Files, 1938-2010; 1.56 Linear Feet in 1 record carton, 1 oversize box, and 1 half manuscript box
  - "An Appeal on the Behalf of Parish of Mullaghbawn" by Archibishop Co. Armagh, Rev. Dr. A'Dalton, 1946 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Armagh Winner 100th Anniversary Photo Album, 1994 (Box 11)
  - Brennan, Thomas G., Feb 16, 1942 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Byrne, James, undated (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Carvill, Frank, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Correspondence: Personal, 1990, undated (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Duffy, Brendan, 1977-1978 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Glencarn Hotel, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Henning, John F., 1966 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - "Home for the Heart: The Story of Irish Immigration," Irish American Heritage Museum Exhibit Catalog, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - The Irish Advocate Newspaper, Feb 15, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Irish American Heritage Museum, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Irish Counties' Athletic Union gold bond, 1907 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Irish Institute Photographs, 1972, undated (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - The Irish World and American Industrial Liberator and Gaelic American, May 22, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Killeavey Memorial Park Committee, Jul 1960 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Makem, Tommy, 1988-2007 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - McGeough, Father Kevin, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - New York Irish Center: Annual Dinner Dance, 2010 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - O'Fiaich, Cardinal Tomas: General, 1977-1990 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - O'Fiaich, Cardinal Tomas: Memorial Fund, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - O'Fiaich, Cardinal Tomas: Newspaper Clippings, 1979-1990 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Royal Marine Corps and IRA Article in The Irish People, Oct 7, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - St. Patrick's Day Parade, 1939-1995 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Sheet Music, after 1957 (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Smyth, Cornelius, 1941-1942 (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - The Society for the Propagation of the Faith [Francis Callaghan], 1973 (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Steffens, Father Albert, 1938-1952 (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - An Taifreann [Mass in Irish], undated (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - United Irish Counties Association, 1957, 1977, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 49)
- Series III: Ancient Order of Hibernians, Ladies Auxiliary, 4.92 Linear Feet in 2 card boxes, 2 oversize flat boxes, and 2 record cartons
  - 150th Anniversary: General, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 2, Folder 1)
  - 150th Anniversary: Dinner Dance, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - 150th Anniversary: Newspapers, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - 150th Anniversary: Publications, 1985-1986 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Artifacts: Gavel, Name Badges, Pin, undated (Box 9)
  - Catholic Action Reports, 1963-1972 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Centennial Celebration, 1994 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Cocktail Party and Dinner Dance Programs, 1973-1986 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Cocktail Party and Dinner Dance Programs, 1979, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Cocktail Party and Dinner Dance Programs, 1987-1991 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Cocktail Party and Dinner Dance Programs, 1993-1994 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Cocktail Party and Dinner Dance Programs, 1994-1997 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Cocktail Party and Dinner Dance Programs, 1998-1999 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Constitution, undated (Box 4, Folder 15, Folder 14)
  - Communion Breakfasts, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Corporate Communion Mass, 1978-1979 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Corporate Communion Mass, 1989-1999 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Division 29, 1979-1997 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Financial Reports, 1993-1998 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Forms, undated (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Ermina Guilfoyle Burial Fund, 1996 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Al O'Hagan, undated (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Irish Hunger Memorial and Mass, 1996-1997 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Sara I.V. Lalor, 1998 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Letter to State President Regarding Dues, 1994 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Kathleen Mattesich, 1997 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Mayor's Liberty Awards, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Meeting Minutes, 1976-1979 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - National Convention Photographs, Aug 1956 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - National Organization, 1974-1992 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - New York County Board: Annual Reports, 1973-1978 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - New York County Board: Annual Reports, 1985-2001 (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - New York County Board: General, 1971-1995 (Box 4, Folder 35, Folder 34)
  - New York County Board: General, 1985-1996 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - New York County Board: Meeting Minutes, 1972-1975 (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - New York County Board: Meeting Notes and Minutes, 1971-1976 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - New York County Board: Officers and Members, 1977-1978 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - New York County Board: Photographs, undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - New York State, 1989-2003 (Box 5, Folder 6, Folder 5, Folder 4)
  - New York State: Convention Proceedings, 1985, 1991 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - New York State: Convention Proceedings, 1993, 1995 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1976-1987 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - "Nuns of the Battlefield" / Civil War Nurses / Calvary Cemetery, 1993-1997 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Personal Materials, 1979-1997 (Box 5, Folder 11, Folder 12, Folder 13)
  - Photographs, 1966-1974, 1995 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Renaming Division, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Ribbons and Badges, undated (Box 8)
  - Ritual Handbooks, undated (Box 5, Folder 16, Folder 17)
  - Sashes and Banners, undated (Box 7)
  - Scrapbook, 1979-1997 (Box 6)
  - St. James Church Renovation, 1997 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - St. Patrick's Day: Greeting Cards, 1993 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - St. Patrick's Day Parade: General, 1949, 1975-1998 (Box 5, Folder 20, Folder 21, Folder 22)
  - St. Patrick's Day Parade: Programs, 1984-2000 (Box 5, Folder 23, Folder 24, Folder 25)
  - St. Patrick's Day Parade: Programs, 1993-1997 (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - St. Patrick's Day Parade: Rules and Regulations, Dec 1987 (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Supplies and Jewelry Catalog, undated (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - Totebag, undated (Box 7)
  - University of Notre Dame Hibernian Fund, 1979 (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - Woman of the Year Award, 1998 (Box 5, Folder 32)